We are basically moving on to the exercise part where we've talked about how to actually use
types within the options API for its core functionality, and so your exercise now is to take
the dish page that we see here, and now you're going to reapply all that stuff, right?
You got to make sure you convert it to TypeScript, then go ahead and type the data.
Go ahead and type the computer properties and the methods, whatever makes sense to you.
So, we have our dishes page, and actually let me go ahead and before I forget, let me switch
the branch to finish so that we add the solution as we go.
So, inside of here, first thing first, we want to use TypeScript, so let's go ahead and make
it language TypeScript, and then once again import defined component, starting to, I'm
going to start to use AutoComplete now, now that you all know where these things are coming from,
so the fine component goes here, let's just collapse that, collapse that, much better, less scrolling.
Okay, so the next thing we need to do now is we need to define the shape of the data,
so we can type data shape, and we know filter text is going to be a string,
and then we want the dish list to be an array of dish, but dish does not exist yet.
So, I'm going to go ahead over to dish card over here, and I'm going to grab this here,
we're going to open up types, and then we're going to drop a suit alphabetical order,
just to make it a little bit easier to follow, export TypeDish.
Now that we have this exported, we can now import the TypeDish, there you go, from types,
perfect, everything works as expected. Then over here, we'll do the same thing, import TypeDish.
Looks like it's not giving me that, that's fine, and then there we go, so we have our dish,
so we've modularized our dish type, and now we're using in two files, and finally we have one
more thing, which is I believe it's show to do, show new form. Form, Boolean, rate, so now what are we doing?
We're returning, we're saying that this is going to be the data shape, and so we take a look now,
this is good, we have a bunch of dishes, dish list is an array of dishes, this is fantastic,
and so I guess something actually probably worth mentioning is you might have noticed that
I tend to notice my arrays with like the thing lists rather than just a plural,
so instead of dishes or restaurants, I found that one off errors when it comes to typing those things,
it happens a lot, so dish list just makes it really explicit, you tend the autocomplete
a little bit better, and you won't dismiss like the one letter, one typing, so that's just
a little convention that I do to kind of offset some of that. Okay, so then okay, inside a
computer, let's go ahead and do some things here, we got an array of dishes, because that's what we're
filtering for, and then just for the sake of documenting a little bit more, the argument is a dish type,
which is great, and number of dishes is going to be a number, we don't want that to ever change,
because that's what we're actually rendering when we're counting the thing, and then inside of
methods, both of our payloads are just going to be the dish type, because that's what we're doing,
right, we're adding something to the dish, and then we're deleting something from the dish,
and this is great, and then actually just to annotate this one to there's another filter here,
that will take care of that, and then finally, hide form doesn't do anything, and then mounted,
we have, nope, there's nothing really to do there, at this point, so okay, that is the solution
for the exercise that we just went through. You might have noticed that I'm typing take,
instead of git, this is not a typo, this is actually an extension that is built to
await take git, there we go. So it's basically a text interface for git, so basically you'll notice
that rather than doing like git status and seeing what's available, and then having to be like
git, at source, and have to figure that out, which takes a while, takes status gives me like
basically a little UI, to be like, oh, actually, I forgot, these are not, they were already staged,
but you can see that I can actually see what stages different files are in, and it's easy to
individually select it with my keyboard, I won't dive into how to use this, but in case you want to
look into it, it's just a little bit of quality life improvement that I like to use for my command line
git. So this is jumping ahead a little bit, but I don't want to lose the context on this question.
So the question here from Daniel in the chat is around the idea of using generics in type script
along the extend. So I want to show you how things used to look. Basically, how you used to
actually use type script on view two, what you did is like view extend thing, and what it basically
allows you to do is like define a bunch of different properties on it, so resuming on this, you'll see
that it's like data methods, and so interface, again, for those who have used type script before,
think of it as a different kind, a different way to define objects in type script. That's all you
need to know right now. There's a lot of argument between which one you should use. Just think
of another, another, and alias for type for now. And so this allows you to create like generic type.
So the concept of generics in type script is a messy topic. In my opinion, and I think it's where
a lot of people actually get messed up, because it's one thing to annotate what you intend to do.
It's another than abstracted into generic concepts that then oftentimes when you look at
type script generics, you'll notice that whenever you see single letters in type script stuff,
that's when you basically, they're using generics, because they're basically placeholder variables.
We're, I will be very explicit. We're not covering that in this, because I do think it just,
it tends to digest just a little too far deep for people when they're getting started with type
script. Most people can just use the straight annotation, and that will already do wonders
for helping them just document their code a little bit better. But for those that are interested in
type theory, I don't want to leave y'all behind too. And so just so you know, rather than having
an extent, the question here is in view three with a defined component, where does it go from here?
There is a great blog post here, where he talks about how it works. And so basically, you can see
here for those wondering, imagine you want to have like a function that generates a specific type of
component, where it comes with these types every single time. So these are generally called factories,
so you can see here that like it's an input select, but we want very specific things to get
attached to it. And so there is the way where basically you can define a component that does take
these generic, you see these T's here, so you can define it, pass it in. There is the way for it to
happen. So if you understand what generic are, you're interested in this, I will make sure that this
is at it as a resource. Okay, so now that we've had like the core functionality of options API,
sort of taking care of, we're going to start moving our way now into composition API.